Once you have entered the information
into Excel, it is then time to apply
some formatting to enhance the meaning
and appearance so that it looks
professional and it displays the
information clearly to an audience.
So as you can see at the
moment it's all quite simple.
It's just simply text, there's no spacing.
There is no formatting being
applied, no colours, no borders,
no shading, anything like that.
So what we're going to do is I'm
going to demonstrate how you can apply
some formatting to this information.
Now, Excel is very similar to
Word and PowerPoint in that it
has obviously the font group.
There's a slight difference that it
has what's called the alignment group.
And this is how you can
align your text in the cells.
And also you can have the
option to merge cells and center
cells, and also a wrap text.
So I'll have a look at some of these
in here, and you can also apply styles
and format the information as a table.
So the first thing I want to do is
I need to space this information out
because it does seem all compressed and
it isn't as clear as I would like it.
So, what I'll do is I'm going to
widen the rows and the columns, just
so that the information is clear.
So if I want to widen them all evenly,
I can click on the little triangle
in the top corner and select that.
And as you can see, it's
selected all of the worksheet.
So if I know click in-between rows one and
two, and then hold the mouse button down
and just drag it down, it automatically
widens all of those rows evenly.
And again, I can do that with the columns.
If I click between B and C, if
I widen them to that, it will
automatically widen the columns evenly.
So now that I have all the
information there, as you can see,
the information in column A is being
cut off and there's two options here.
I can widen that one and it
will automatically widen those.
So rather than do that, I just
want to widen that column on its
own, so I click away and then I
can just widen that  individually.
It doesn't widen the other columns
anymore, that only occurs if you select
everything and then you start widening
it will automatically apply that to
all the rows or columns, depending
on what you're changing the size of.
So now I'm happy with that.
As you can see, the text is aligned
to the top on row one, and it is
aligned to the text - is aligned
to the top everywhere, basically.
Now I want to center align everything.
And what actually, what I'll do is I will
bottom align the text in the top row.
So that's now at the top.
And if I go up to the alignment and
I'm going to select bottom, so that
aligns it to the bottom and everything
else, I'm going to align to the center.
So that's all now showing clearly so it's
directly central within each of the cells.
So it may be a case that I want to
reduce the width of that column there.
So this will be relevant
to the wrapping text.
So if I select that column and select
wrap text, nothing happens initially.
But if I reduce the size of that column,
it will automatically wrap the text.
And if I undo the wrap text, as you
can see the information, I would have
to widen the column again so I can
apply wrap text or take that off.
And if I don't have it on, I
need to widen that column so
all the information is clear.
In addition to that, I can
apply the standard formatting.
So for this top row here,
I'm going to make it bold.
And all of the information in column
A, I'm going to make bold as well.
And I'm going to change
everything and the font to Arial.
So I need to select everything,
click on the font and select Arial.
And that's changed everything to
Arial size 11, which I'm happy with.
I'm also going to apply
some shading to the top row.
So I'm going to use the fill for that.
So if I go up and use the fill
colour, and I'm just going to
select a blue background for that.
And as you can see, I could then
apply various other colour formatting.
So you may want to display the
information and the total income.
So that's a financial figure.
You may want to display that
in a different colour to the
information that's in the main body.
You may want to display the
average sales as a different colour.
So then that gives you the option of
making information stand out, so if all
of the price and the total income were
in green, that could be in yellow, the
rest of the information could be in blue.
Please bear in mind, though,
that you don't want to overload
the worksheet with colours.
In addition to that, as you can see, none
of the information has borders around it.
So what I'd like to do is apply a
border to all of the information.
So again, all I would do is highlight
all of the information and on the
borders tool and select all borders.
And that just breaks the
information up even further.
So as well as that, you also have
the option to format the information
as a table, and you can also
apply styles to the information.
So you could have a look and play
around with the table styles, as you
can see, these are very similar to
the table styles that you had in Word.
So if I just clicked on that one there, I
haven't selected all of the information,
but, so I'll just cancel that.
If I select everything and then decide
that I'm going to go for a table
colour of grey and select OK, it will
automatically apply that to the table.
As you can see the error buttons have
comeback on relating to the fact that
the price isn't included in the formula,
but I'm just going to ignore that.
And also it has added the filter buttons.
And again, I'm just going to click
in that cell and I'll go to sort and
filter and remove those, 'cause I don't
want those on, and I'm quite happy
with all of the information there.
And just to ensure that all of the
rows and columns are set out evenly,
I'll just click on the triangle again.
Double click.
And again, double click on that and that
has reduced it back to the way it was.
So I now need to change the formatting
on there and just click ignore error.
And I'm quite happy with that there.
So you can have a play around
with the various formatting tools
within there and make changes.
If you're not happy with anything, you
can just undo it by Control and Z and
then you can apply more formatting.
So just have a practice with that.